Office of the President Records UA001
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Office of the President Records
1824 -- 2020
1925 -- 2014
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Office of the President
Ballou II, Hosea
Miner, Alonzo Ames
Capen, Elmer Hewitt
Hamilton, Frederick William
Hooper, William Leslie
Bumpus, Hermon Carey
Cousens, John Albert
Miller, George Stewart
Carmichael, Leonard
Wessell, Nils Yngve
Mead, Leonard Chapin
Hallowell, Burton Crosby
Mayer, Jean
DiBiaggio, John A.
Bacow, Lawrence S.
Monaco, A. P. (Anthony Philip), 1959 --
UA001
262.42 Linear Feet 279 boxes and 18 oversize folders
1 Artifact(s)
107 Digital Object(s)
Arrangement
This collection is organized in 20 series: Hosea Ballou 2d; Alonzo Ames Miner, records; Elmer Hewitt Capen, administrative records and related papers; Frederick William Hamilton, administrative records and related papers; William Leslie Hooper, administrative records and related papers; Hermon Carey Bumpus, administrative records and related papers; John Albert Cousens, administrative records and related papers; George Stewart Miller, administrative records and related papers; Leonard Carmichael, administrative records and related papers; Nils Yngve Wessell, administrative records and related papers; Leonard Chapin Mead, administrative records and related papers; Burton Crosby Hallowell, administrative records and related papers; Jean Mayer, administrative records and related papers; John DiBiaggio, administrative records and related papers; Historical presidential correspondence; Artifacts; Annual report of the president; Lawrence Seldon Bacow, administrative records and related papers; Anthony P. Monaco administrative records and related papers; and Unprocessed accessions.
Custodial History
All material accessioned prior to 1997 was originally arranged by subject by Russell Miller. No attempt was made to recreate original order, although material relating to administering the collection was removed to the documentation files of the collection in the archives. Also, some material in the early presidents' records were assembled from other sources when the material was brought into the library in the late 1960s.
The busts of Hosea Ballou, Alonzo Ames Miner, and Elmer Hewitt Capen, which had been on loan from the Art Gallery, were returned to them on May 7, 2018, by Collections Management Archivist Adrienne Pruitt.
Scope and Contents
This record group contains the administrative records--including correspondence, financial reocrds, newspaper clippings, photographs, publications, reports, speeches, and subject files--of the presidents of Tufts. Information about all aspects of the college and university are found in the records of the Office of the President. Often this material is in summary form. Records prior to 1976 were inconsistently kept and are even less complete for nineteenth-century presidents.
Most of the collections of the early presidents contain personal correspondence, teaching material, and writings.
Materials regarding John P. Marshall (acting president, 1861-1862) are located in his vertical file.
Biographical / Historical
The Office of the President is responsible for regulating and overseeing the general administration of the University. Along with various administrative duties, each year the president prepares an annual report which is delivered to the Board of Trustees. This state of the university report generally includes information about past and present college affairs and policies, as well as future plans and suggestions. The Office of the President was the first, and for a time only, administrative office. Originally, the president performed virtually all administrative duties. Presidents usually were members of the faculty as well. In the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries, as administrative functions became more complex, the duties of the president were spread among other administrators. With the professionalization of college and university administration in the mid-twentieth century, specialized administrative offices were created, and faculty no longer performed dual roles of educators and administrators.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list. This collection may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.
Content Warning
This finding aid contains language that may be offensive or outdated. Because such language is in titles or direct transcription of published materials, it has not been changed. Keeping this language intact provides the most accurate depiction of the creators' intent, and can potentially tell us important things about bigotry and bias on the part of the creators, or in a particular historical context. It can also preserve terms formerly applied by a group to self-identify that have since fallen out of common usage. For more information on DCA's content warning policy please visit our website.
Administration and Governance -- Governance; Administration and Governance -- Accreditation
- Hosea Ballou 2d, records, 1824 -- 1952; 1824 -- 1861; UA001.001; 4.5 Linear Feet; 1 Artifact(s); 3 Digital Object(s)
  Scope and Contents
  The collection contains the earliest records of teaching at Tufts, photographs, personal correspondence between Ballou and, especially, T.J. Sawyer, as well as some teaching material and some of Ballou's own school books. Dates range from the early 1820s through Ballou's death in 1861. Photographs date from 1858 through 1952. The student records include a recitation (grade) book from about 1854, and records of absences from 1856-61. Teaching material includes notes from lectures on, for example, "The Fall of Rome," "History of the English Language," and "Questions from Bowens Politial Economy." There is one folder of photographs that were added to the collection at some later point. These include original and copy photographic prints (dates are assigned based on the original image) of Ballou, his homestead in Vermont, and various memorials to him at Tufts.
  Biographical Note:
  Hosea Ballou (1796-1861) was born in Guilford, Vermont in 1796. He was a Universalist clergyman, theologian, and historian. He presided over the parishes of Roxbury and Medford Massachusetts from 1821-1852, published the "Ancient History of Universalism" in 1829, and received an honorary Doctorate of Divinity from, and became an Overseer of, Harvard University in 1845. Having been one of the biggest influences in the establishment of the College, Hosea Ballou 2d became the first President of Tufts College in 1853. He was its first professor of History and Intellectual Philosophy. It would be thirty years after his death before another professor at Tufts was able to match his scholarly and teaching ability in that field. Hosea Ballou 2d established the college's first curriculum which led to the Bachelor of Arts degree. He died in office in 1861. His personal library remains as a legacy to the university to this day.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged alphabetically by subject.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Ballou family material, 1855 -- 1873; UA001.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, UA001.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: T.J. Sawyer, 1838 -- 1861; UA001.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Tompkins, Tweed, Fay, and Thayer, 1848 -- 1859; UA001.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1831 -- 1861; UA001.001.001.00005 (Box 1)
  - Recitation record, 1853 -- 1854; UA001.001.001.00006 (Box 1)
  - Teaching material: The Feudal System, UA001.001.001.00007 (Box 1)
  - Teaching material: Philosophy and the Reformation, UA001.001.001.00008 (Box 1)
  - Record of absences and leaves, 1860 -- 1861; UA001.001.001.00009 (Box 1)
  - Manuscript book: The Psalms, UA001.001.001.00010 (Box 1)
  - Manuscript book: Geography of the New Testament, UA001.001.001.00011 (Box 1)
  - Manuscript book: Commentatio Auctore Moshemio, UA001.001.001.00012 (Box 1)
  - Manuscript book: Genuineness of the Gospels, UA001.001.001.00013 (Box 1)
  - Manuscript book: Justin Martyr, UA001.001.001.00014 (Box 1)
  - Manuscript book: Clemens Alexandrinus and Maximus Confessor, UA001.001.001.00015 (Box 1)
  - Address at the Opening of Tufts College, 1855; UA001.001.001.00016; Ballou, Hosea, 1796-1861 (Box 1)
  - Manuscript book: Excerpta 2, UA001.001.002.00001 (Box 2)
  - Manuscript book: Excerpta 3, UA001.001.002.00002 (Box 2)
  - Manuscript book: Memoranda, 1828 -- 1838; UA001.001.003.00001 (Box 3)
  - Teaching material: Historic Sketches and Tables (oversize), UA001.001.003.00002 (Box 3)
  - Manuscript book: Hebrew Grammar (oversize), UA001.001.003.00003 (Box 3)
  - Teaching material: Chronology of the French Revolution (oversize), UA001.001.003.00004 (Box 3)
  - Manuscript book: Observations from the White Mountains, UA001.001.004.00001 (Box 4)
  - Manuscript book: Grammar and Language of the New Testament, UA001.001.004.00002 (Box 4)
  - Manuscript book: Translations from German on the Origins of Sin, UA001.001.004.00003 (Box 4)
  - Manuscript books (3): Tennemann, UA001.001.004.00004 (Box 4)
  - Manuscript book: Apostolic Fathers, UA001.001.004.00005 (Box 4)
  - Manuscript book: Gaelic, UA001.001.004.00006 (Box 4)
  - Manuscript book: Language Exercises and New Hampshire Journal, UA001.001.004.00007 (Box 4)
  - Manuscript book: Journal of Travels in New Hampshire, UA001.001.004.00008 (Box 4)
  - Manuscript book: Journal of European Travels, UA001.001.004.00009 (Box 4)
  - Record of leaves and absences, 1856; UA001.001.004.00010 (Box 4)
  - Record of leaves and absences and miscellaneous memoranda, 1858 -- 1859; UA001.001.004.00011 (Box 4)
  - Record of leaves and absences and miscellaneous memoranda, 1859; UA001.001.004.00012 (Box 4)
  - Teaching material: The Fall of Rome, UA001.001.005.00001 (Box 5)
  - Manuscript book: Collection of Texts from the New Testament, UA001.001.005.00002 (Box 5)
  - Manuscript book: On the Doctrine of Necessity, UA001.001.005.00003 (Box 5)
  - Manuscript book: Excerpta. No. 5, Scripture and Ancient Geography, UA001.001.005.00004 (Box 5)
  - Manuscript book: Index to a Theological Common-Place Book, UA001.001.006.00001 (Box 6)
  - Record of absences, 1859 -- 1860; UA001.001.006.00002 (Box 6)
  - Teaching material: Questions from Bowens Political Economy, UA001.001.006.00003 (Box 6)
  - Teaching material: Medieval History, UA001.001.006.00004 (Box 6)
  - Teaching material: History of the English Language, UA001.001.006.00005 (Box 6)
  - Manuscript book: French Grammar, 1828; UA001.001.006.00006 (Box 6)
  - Manuscript book: Biblical Commentary and the History of France, 1832; UA001.001.006.00007 (Box 6)
  - Photographs, 1861 -- 1900; UA001.001.007.00001 (Box 7)
  - Photographs, 1858 -- 1952; UA001.001.007.00002 (Box 7)
  - Hosea Ballou, 1860; UA001.001.007.00003 (Box Shared 4)
  - Hosea Ballou, 1858; UA001.001.007.00004 (Box Shared 4)
  - Hosea Ballou, 1858; UA001.001.007.00005 (Box Shared 4)
  - Hosea Ballou, 1870; UA001.001.007.00006 (Box Large Map Case 2 Drawer 6)
  - Balance (scale) donated by First Universalist Sabbath School., 1857; UA001.001.007.00007 (Box Shared 10)
    This balance was constructed by the well known maker of philosophical instruments, E.S. Ritchie, 313 Washington St., Boston. The First Universalist Church was located in the North End of Boston at the corner of Hanover and N. Bennett Streets. In 1857 the minister of the church was the Rev. Sebastian Streeter, who undoubtedly was solicited by the president of the college, Hosea Ballou II for financial aid in initiating the study of science at the small struggling college on the Hill in Medford.
  - Excerpta Historica, Critica, Miscellenea, 1824; UA001.001.008.00001 (Box 8)
  - Hosea Ballou 2d portrait, 1879; UA001.001.DO.00067; Unknown (Box Shared 140)
    cabinet card, two copies
    Boston (Mass.); Portraits; People; College presidents; photographic print; Ballou, Hosea, 2d; Office of the President
  - Hosea Ballou homestead in Guilford, Vermont, 1952; UA001.001.DO.00068; Unknown (Box Shared 140)
    Buildings; Barns; Ballou, Hosea, 2d
- Alonzo Ames Miner, records, 1842 -- 1939; 1850 -- 1883; UA001.002; 3.1 Linear Feet; 1 Artifact(s); 4 Digital Object(s)
  The collection contains genealogy, Miner estate account books, newsclippings, correspondence from 1859-1895, published speeches and sermons given by Miner, photographs, and a large amount of materials dealing with Alonzo Amos Miner's involvement in the Temperance movement, relief committees, and peace congresses of the mid-to-late nineteenth century. Organizations covered in this collection include the National Prohibition Alliance and the American Total Abstinence Society. Photographic prints dated from 1866 to 1939 include original and copy photographic prints (dates are assigned based on the original image) of Miner and his family coat of arms.
  All material accessioned prior to 1997 was arranged by subject, and no attempt was made to recreate original order. Material relating to administering the collection was removed to the documentation files of the collection in the archives.
  Biographical note:
  Alonzo Ames Miner (1814-95) was born in Lempster, NH, on August 17, 1814. As a young man, Miner taught school in various rural towns in Vermont and New Hampshire. In 1839 he was ordained a Universalist minister. In 1848 he succeeded Hosea Ballou (the elder) as pastor of the Second Universalist Church of Boston, a post he held until his death. Although Miner had little formal education himself, he was firmly devoted to the cause of education in Massachusetts at all levels. He was at various times a member of the Board of Trustees of Tufts College, the Board of Overseers of Harvard, the Massachusetts State Board of Education and other secular and religious educational institutions.
  Alonzo Miner was involved in many moral and civic organizations. He was very active in the Temperance movement of the mid-nineteenth century on a local and national level, local work relief committees, national and state peace congresses, and other local civic groups.
  Miner was appointed president of Tufts College in 1862, after the untimely death the previous year of Hosea Ballou, 2d. According to the terms of the agreement, Miner continued to hold his position at the Second Universalist Church and received no salary for serving as the president of the college. He is the only president not to live on campus. Miner brought the college back from the brink of financial ruin, and developed many new educational programs. He died on June 14, 1895.
  - Prohibition, UA001.002.001.00001 (Box 1)
  - Inauguration, 1862; UA001.002.001.00002 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1862 -- 1895; UA001.002.001.00003 (Box 1)
  - Speeches and addresses (printed), 1855 -- 1883; UA001.002.001.00004 (Box 1)
  - Sermons (printed), 1852 -- 1884; UA001.002.001.00005 (Box 1)
  - Dated and undated correspondence, 1842 -- 1848; UA001.002.001.00006 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1855 -- 1866; UA001.002.001.00007 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1867 -- 1894; UA001.002.001.00008 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: personal, 1859 -- 1870; UA001.002.002.00001 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: personal, 1871 -- 1875; UA001.002.002.00002 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: personal, 1876 -- 1882; UA001.002.002.00003 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: personal, 1883 -- 1885; UA001.002.002.00004 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: personal, 1886 -- 1891; UA001.002.002.00005 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: personal, 1891 -- 1895; UA001.002.002.00006 (Box 2)
  - Records: public life, UA001.002.003.00001 (Box 3)
  - Genealogical and family, UA001.002.003.00002 (Box 3)
  - Estate of Alonzo A. Miner, UA001.002.003.00003 (Box 3)
  - Account book for the Miner Estate, UA001.002.003.00004 (Box 3)
  - Account book for the Miner Estate, UA001.002.003.00005 (Box 3)
  - Account book for the Miner Estate, UA001.002.003.00006 (Box 3)
  - Photographs, 1870; UA001.002.004.00001 (Box 4)
    - Alonzo Ames Miner, 1870; UA001.002.004.00001.00001; Unknown (Box 4)
      People; Portraits; College presidents; Miner, Alonzo Ames; Office of the President
  - Photographs, 1866 -- 1939; UA001.002.004.00002 (Box 4)
  - Alonzo Ames Miner's headstone, 1900; UA001.002.004.00003; Unknown (Box Shared 4)
    Memorials; Graves; College presidents; Miner, Alonzo Ames
  - Alonzo Ames Miner, 1870; UA001.002.004.00004 (Box Large Map Case 2 Drawer 6)
  - Alonzo A. Miner, 1860; UA001.002.DO.00094; Unknown (Box Shared 84)
    Portraits; People; College presidents; Office of the President, Alonzo Ames Miner, records; Miner, Alonzo Ames; Office of the President
  - Alonzo A. Miner, 1850; UA001.002.DO.00095; Unknown (Box Shared 84)
    cartes-de-visite
  - Miner coat of arms, UA001.002.DO.00096; Unknown (Box Shared 84)
    Coats of arms; Office of the President, Alonzo Ames Miner, records; Miner, Alonzo Ames; Office of the President
- Elmer Hewitt Capen, administrative records and related papers, 1854 -- 1905; 1854 -- 1906; UA001.003; 1.95 Linear Feet; 1 Artifact(s); 2 Digital Object(s)
  This series contains correspondence from 1854-1903; clippings; Elmer Capen's Inauguration materials from 1875; his writings and publications from 1872-1902; photographs; and correspondence, notices, and memorial publications on the occasion of his death in 1905. Photographs, dating from 1875 through 1889, include original and copy photographic prints (dates are assigned based on the original image) of Capen.
  Elmer Hewitt Capen (1838-1905) was born on April 5, 1838 in Stoughton, Massachusetts. He graduated from Tufts in 1860, practiced law for a short time, and then became a Universalist minister. While still an undergraduate, Capen was elected to, and served in, the Massachusetts House of Representatives. He relinquished his seat after one term in order to finish his studies and graduate with his class.
  This series is arranged chronologically within each subject.
  - Correspondence, 1854 -- 1905; UA001.003.001.00001 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, UA001.003.001.00002 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, UA001.003.001.00003 (Box 1)
  - Inauguration, 1875; UA001.003.002.00001 (Box 2)
  - Writings and publications, 1872 -- 1902; UA001.003.002.00002 (Box 2)
  - Funeral, UA001.003.002.00003 (Box 2)
  - Photographs, 1875 -- 1889; UA001.003.003.00001 (Box 3)
  - Photographs, 1875 -- 1889; UA001.003.003.00002 (Box 3)
  - Elmer Hewitt Capen, 1880; UA001.003.003.00003 (Box Shared 4)
  - Elmer Hewitt Capen, 1880 -- 1889; UA001.003.003.00004 (Box Shared 4)
  - Elmer Hewitt Capen, 1880 -- 1889; UA001.003.003.00005 (Box Shared 4)
  - Elmer Hewitt Capen, 1870; UA001.003.003.00006 (Box Large Map Case 2 Drawer 6)
  - Portrait of E.H. Capen with kind regards from P.T. Barnum, 1886; UA001.003.004.00001 (Box 4)
  - Elmer Capen, 1884; UA001.003.DO.00072; Unknown (Box Shared 141)
    cabinet card
    Portraits; People; College presidents; Office of the President, Elmer Hewitt Capen, records; cartes-de-visite; Capen, Elmer Hewitt; Office of the President
  - Elmer Capen, 1900; UA001.003.DO.00073; Unknown (Box Shared 141)
    Portraits; People; College presidents; Office of the President, Elmer Hewitt Capen, records; Capen, Elmer Hewitt; Office of the President
- Frederick William Hamilton, administrative records and related papers, 1880 -- 1912; 1905 -- 1912; UA001.004; 0.8 Linear Feet; 2 Digital Object(s)
  This collection contains correspondence from 1905-12, clippings, F.W. Hamilton's published writings from 1906-1912, 1906 inauguration material, and photographs. Photographs, dating from 1880, are largely undated and include original and copy photographic prints (dates are assigned based on the original image) of Hamilton and a painted portrait of him.
  Frederick William Hamilton (1860-1940) was born in Portland, Maine in 1860. He graduated from Tufts in 1880 with his A.B. and in 1886 with his A.M. in English literature and philosophy. He received an honorary D.D. from Tufts College in 1889, and an honorary LL.D. from St. Lawrence in 1906. He was a Universalist clergyman, businessman, and president of Tufts from 1905-1912.
  - Correspondence, 1905 -- 1910; UA001.004.001.00001 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1910 -- 1911; UA001.004.001.00002 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1911 -- 1912; UA001.004.001.00003 (Box 1)
  - Dental School correspondence, 1907 -- 1912; UA001.004.001.00004 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, UA001.004.001.00005 (Box 1)
  - Inauguration, 1906; UA001.004.001.00006 (Box 1)
  - Writings and publications, 1906 -- 1912; UA001.004.001.00007 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, 1889 -- 1890; UA001.004.002.00001 (Box 2)
  - Frederick William Hamilton, 1907; UA001.004.002.00002 (Box Large Map Case 2 Drawer 6)
  - Frederick William Hamilton, 1905; UA001.004.DO.00087; Unknown (Box Shared 140)
    Portraits; People; College presidents; Office of the President, Frederick William Hamilton, records; Hamilton, Frederick William; Office of the President
  - Frederick William Hamilton, 1880; UA001.004.DO.00088; Unknown (Box Shared 140)
- William Leslie Hooper, administrative records and related papers, 1877 -- 1918; 1912 -- 1918; UA001.005; 0.5 Linear Feet; 2 Digital Object(s)
  This collection contains photographs; personal and administrative correspondence; and papers by W.L. Hooper on venereal diseases, and the effects of magnetism on specific heat. The photographs, dating from the 1880s and 90s, are largely undated and include original cabinet cards and copy photographic prints (dates are assigned based on the original image). Most are formal portraits of Hooper.
  William Leslie Hooper (1855-1918) was born in Halifax, Nova Scotia in 1855. He received his A.B. from Tufts in 1877, and his A.M. in 1878. Hooper also received an honorary PhD. in 1898 and an LL.D. in 1915. He was instructor of Mathematics and Applied Physics at Bromfield Academy and became its principal in 1880. In 1883 he became assistant professor of physics at Tufts. In 1890, W.L. Hooper became professor of electrical engineering. Having been commended by the Trustees for his contributions to the engineering department at Tufts and his successful fundraising abilities, Professor Hooper was made acting president of Tufts in 1912. He returned to his position in the electrical engineering department in 1914. In addition to his teaching duties, Professor Hooper continued to write extensively in the field of electrical engineering and worked actively as an electrical consultant for many area companies. W.L. Hooper died in his home on Professors Row in 1918.
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  - Scientific Papers, 1914; UA001.005.001.00001 (Box 1)
    Three scientific papers written by W. L. Hooper, including one publication from 1914.
  - Correspondence, 1890 -- 1918; UA001.005.001.00002 (Box 1)
    Most correspondence from 1910-1918.
  - Photographs, 1887 -- 1915; UA001.005.002.00001 (Box 2)
  - Photographs, 1887 -- 1915; UA001.005.002.00002 (Box 2)
  - William Leslie Hooper, 1900; UA001.005.002.00003 (Box Large Map Case 2 Drawer 6)
  - W.L. Hooper in front of his home, 1913; UA001.005.DO.00089; Unknown (Box Shared 84)
    Portraits; People; College presidents; Office of the President, William Leslie Hooper, records; Hooper, William Leslie; Office of the President
  - William Leslie Hooper, 1877; UA001.005.DO.00090; Unknown (Box Shared 140)
- Hermon Carey Bumpus, administrative records and related papers, 1896 -- 1943; 1913 -- 1919; UA001.006; 0.8 Linear Feet; 3 Digital Object(s)